Mss.919.8.D73u
American Philosophical Society
[Under the midnight sun].
Circa 1869
Mss.919.8.D73u
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 39 x 50 cm folio
A companion volume of albumen prints taken by William Bradford and other members of the "Panther", in Greenland, in the summer of 1869. This voyage is described in Hayes, I. I. The Land of Desolation; William Bradford was the Captain of the Panther.
1 volume.
Dorr, Dalton.
Volume 1
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Hayes A. Dorr, 1973.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: A bound folio of 92 albumen prints, from 16 x 21 cm. to 29 x 40 cm., are primarily landscapes of icebergs, glaciers, and rock formations. Thirty-five of the prints are ethnographic in nature of Inuit social life and customs, including dwellings, encampments, kayak, oomiak, and portraits in native attire. Images reflect settlements in Krakortok, Sermitsialik, and Upernavik along the west coast of Greenland in 1869. Referenced in the Supplement to a Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society, with descriptive text in Dorr’s journal and Hayes’ work.
Biographical/Historical note
Dalton Dorr (1846-1901) was elected secretary of the Pennsylvania Museum and School of Industrial Art, now known as the Philadelphia Museum of Art, in 1880. In 1887, the title of curator was added to his duties that later culminated in the directorship of the museum in 1892. He administered these three tasks until 1899. Dorr enjoyed traveling. The “Notes of travel made from memoranda in old diaries” (B D735) is a hand-written account of recollections of his excursions. Written in the winter of 1897-1898, the journal presents details of “A Pleasure cruise in Greenland” in the summer of 1869 with marine painter William Bradford, Massachusetts photographers John Dunmore and George Critcherson, and arctic explorer and physician Dr. Isaac I. Hayes. Dr. Hayes’ published work, The Land of Desolation (1872), gives a full description of the Panther’s voyage north along the island’s west coast. From March 1872 to April 1873, Dorr explored “The Indian territory, Colorado and the Pacific Coast” including the Mojave reservation, Fort Yuma, Arizona City, San Diego and San Francisco. Other places noted include trips to Paris (1873), England, Scotland, and Ireland (1882-1884), and a Continental trip (1885). Referenced in the journal, “Under the midnight sun” (919.8 D73u) is the companion bound folio of albumen prints by Bradford, Dunmore and Critcherson of Greenland. The 92 photographs, with hand-written captions, reflect arctic landscapes, native houses, Norse ruins, glaciers, icebergs, bears, and Inuits. The picturesque representations have scientific as well as ethnographic value. A manuscript map of Davis Strait and the west side of Greenland, shows the route of the 1869 Bradford expedition in red.
Related Archival Materials note
Hayes, I. I. (Isaac Israel), 1832-1881. The land of desolation: being a personal narrative of observation and adventure in Greenland (New York, 1872) Call no. 919.8 H32L
Bradford, William, 1823-1892; Hayes, I. I, (Isaac Israel), 1832-1881; Panther (Ship); Albumen prints; Arctic Indians; Arctic regions -- Description and travel.; Arctic regions -- Pictorial works.; Arctic regions--Discovery and exploration; Inuit--Greenland; Maps.
- Photographs, 1869
  - 1. Quiddy Viddy (Newfoundland), 1869
  - 2. Quiddy Viddy (Newfoundland), 1869
  - 3. Petty Harbor (Newfoundland), 1869
  - 4. Petty Harbor (Newfoundland), 1869
  - 5. Julianshaab, 1869
  - 6. Trader's family, Half-breed, Julianshaab-Benedict, 1869
  - 7. Norse Ruins, Krakortok, 1869
  - 8. Norse Ruins, The Church, 1869
  - 9. The Church, 2nd view, 1869
  - 10. The Church, 3rd view, 1869
  - 11. The Church, 4th view, 1869
  - 12. Oomiak, or Women's Boat, 1869
  - 13. Camp at Krakortok, 1869
  - 14. Peter Motzfeldt, Governor of Kraksiment, and part of his family, 1869
  - 15. Esquimaux Girl, "Concordia", 1869
  - 16. Sermitsialik Glacier, North Face, 1869
  - 17. Sermitsialik Glacier, South Face, 1869
  - 18. South Face of Glacier, 2nd view, 1869
  - 19. South Face of Glacier, 3rd view, 1869
  - 20. South Face of Glacier, 4th view, 1869
  - 21. South Face of Glacier, 5th view, showing the "Ice Tongue", 1869
  - 22. Face of Fresh Cleavage from Face of Glacier, 1869
  - 23. The Lateral Thrust of the Glacier, 1869
  - 24. View down the Fiord from the Moraine on North Side of Glacier, 1869
  - 25. Moraine, 2nd view, 1869
  - 26. Moraine, 3rd view, 1869
  - 27. Torrent inder Glacier, at edge of Moraine, 1869
  - 28. Camp on Sermitsialik Glacier, 1869
  - 29. A Walk over the Glacier, 1869
  - 30. A Crevasse on the Glacier, 1869
  - 31. View down Kraksimiut Fiord, from Cliffs beside Glacier, North side, 1869
  - 32. View down the Fiord from South Side of Glacier, 1869
  - 33. Irigtuk Cryolite Mine, Arsuk Mt. in distance, 1869
  - 34. Arsuk Mt., 4400 feet, 1869
  - 35. Arsuk Mt., 2nd view, 1869
  - 36. Arsuk Mt., 3rd view, 1869
  - 37. Arsuk Mt., 4th view, 1869
  - 38. Disco, 1869
  - 39. Disco, 2nd view, 1869
  - 40. Disco, Danish Supply Ships, 1869
  - 41. Disco, Wrecked Whaler, 1869
  - 42. Disco, Sophy and Maria, Half Breed, 1869
  - 43. The Gull Cliffs, near Upernavik, 1869
  - 44. The Gull Cliffs, 2nd view, 1869
  - 45. The Gull Cliffs, 3rd view, 1869
  - 46. The Gull Cliffs, 4th view, 1869
  - 47. The Gull Cliffs, 5th view, 1869
  - 48. Upernavik, 1869
  - 49. Graves, Upernavik, 1869
  - 50. Dr. Rudolf, Governor of Upernavik, 1869
  - 51. Native's House, 1869
  - 52. Native's House, 2nd view, 1869
  - 53. Summer Hut, 1869
  - 54. Hut and Kyack, 1869
  - 55. Esquimauk Family at Disco, 1869
  - 56. Hans, Dr. Hayes old guide, and Family, 1869
  - 57. An Aboriginee, 1869
  - 58. Jensen's House at Tessinsak, 1869
    Scope and Contents note
    No European lives north of this, view taken at midnight.
  - 59. Jensen and Family, 1869
  - 60. Jensen with dog sledge, 1869
  - 61. View from Disco, Seawards, 1869
  - 62. The Shore after a Storm, 1869
  - 63. Sunlight and Shadow, Drift Ice, 1869
  - 64. Sanderson's Hope, 1869
  - 65. Bears retreating over Floe Ice, 1869
  - 66. Trophies of the Chase, 1869
  - 67. Trophies, 2nd view, 1869
  - 68. Trophies, 3rd view, 1869
  - 69. Icebergs, 1869
  - 70. The Sun, Midnight, August 11-12, 1869
  - 71. "An Old Stager", 1869
  - 72. "Braking Up", 1869
  - 73. "A Natural Arch", 1869
  - 74. "Wave Lines", 1869
  - 75. "Hard Aground", 1869
  - 76. Wave Lines, again, 1869
  - 77. Pack Ice, 1869
  - 78. The Ice about the Devil's Thumb, 1869
  - 79. The Devil's Thumb, 1869
  - 80. The Devil'd Thumb, 2nd view, 1869
  - 81. A lead in the Pack, 1869
  - 82. In the Pack Ice, 1869
  - 83. Near View of a Burg, 1869
  - 84. In Melville Bay, 1869
  - 85. In Melville Bay, 2nd view, 1869
  - 86. In Melville Bay, 3rd view, 1869
  - 87. In Melville Bay, 4th view, 1869
  - 88. In Melville Bay, 5th view, 1869
  - 89. In Melville Bay, 6th view, 1869
  - 90. In Melville Bay, 7th view, 1869
  - 91. In Melville Bay, 8th view, 1869
  - 92. Weather and Water Worn, 1869